Guide to the Ipas Records, 1965-2020; 1965-ongoing RL.00617
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ipas records
1965-2020; 1965-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ipas
RL.00617
363 Linear Feet 242 boxes
Ipas works around the world to increase women's ability to exercise their sexual and reproductive rights, especially the right to safe abortion. The collection documents this global nongovernmental organization dedicated to ending preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion.
Access Restrictions
Materials that document the programmatic work of the organization must be at least 5 years old to be eligible for transfer to the Library.
Access to such material, excluding publications, will be restricted for 10 years after initial date of transfer to persons who receive prior written permission from the President and CEO of Donor or his/her designee.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ipas Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2011-2017.
Historical Note
Founded in 1973, Ipas is a nonprofit organization that works around the world to increase women's ability to exercise their sexual and reproductive rights, especially the right to safe abortion. Through local, national, and global partnerships, Ipas seeks to end preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion and to expand women's access to safe, respectful, and comprehensive abortion care, including contraception and related reproductive health information and care. Ipas strives to foster a legal, policy and social environment supportive of women's rights to make their own sexual and reproductive health decisions freely and safely.
Ipas' executive directors and presidents/CEOs since 1973 have been: Elton Kessel 1973-1974, Jorgen Jenk 1974-1976, John Tomaro 1976-1979, Charanne Clarke 1979-1982, Edward Meldahl 1982-1985, Katie Early (McLaurin) 1985-1991, Forrest C. Greenslade 1991-1999, Elizabeth S. Maguire 1999-2015, and John Hetherington starting in 2015.
More information about the organization and its activities can be found on its website: www.ipas.org.
Collection Overview
Collection documents this global nongovernmental organization dedicated to ending preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion. It consists of Ipas publications, including both electronic and printed formats, as well as Latin America and Caribbean Programs material, Africa Programs material, Asia Programs, Marketing/Technology and Logistics/Product Promotion, and Distribution material, Chronological Files, Program Files and Internal Documentation, Executive and Management files, Training and Service Delivery Improvement, Policy Unit files, and Health Systems Research/Research and Evaluation.
Acquired jointly as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture and the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
This collection guide is being regularly updated as materials are added to the archive. Please contact Research Services if you would like to use this collection.
Reproductive health; Right to health care; Human reproductive technology; Human Rights; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Abortion; Women's health services -- United States; Women's health services -- Latin America; Women's health services -- Caribbean Area; Women's health services -- Asia; Women's health services -- Africa; Women -- Health and hygiene; Women's rights; Ipas; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Publications, 1975-2020; 1975-ongoing; 40 boxes; 1.2 gigabytes, approximately 900 electronic files
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains Ipas and non-Ipas publications and audio/visual materials. Electronic publications have been removed from the collection and transferred to Duke's Electronic Records server.
  Access restrictions
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  - 1975-1997, 7 folders of print publications. 19 PDF files comprising 4 publications of electronic publications. Approximately 3 megabytes. (Box 1)
  - 1998, 5 folders of print publications. 1 PDF file comprising 1 electronic publication, approximately 0.1 megabytes. (Box 1)
  - 1999, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 2000, 2 of 3 folders of print publications. 5 PDF files comprising 5 electronic publications. Approximately 0.75 megabytes. (Box 1)
  - 2000, folder 3 of 3 (Box 2)
  - 2001, 6 folders of print publications. 29 PDF files comprising 28 electronic publications, approximately 30 megabytes. (Box 2)
  - 2002, 8 folders of print publications. 24 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 13 megabytes. (Box 2)
  - 2003, 4 of 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Multimedia materials: Advocating for Safe Abortion in Africa (Box 3)
  - 2003, folders 5 through 12 of print publications. 28 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 11 megabytes. (Box 3)
  - 2004, 4 of 6 folders of print publications. 39 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 35 megabytes. (Box 3)
  - 2004, folders 5 to 6 (Box 4)
  - 2005, 8 folders of print publications. 62 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 48 megabytes. (Box 4)
  - 2006, 6 of 9 folders of print publications. 35 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 57 megabytes. (Box 4)
  - 2006, folders 7 to 9 (Box 5)
  - 2007, 4 folders of print publications. 83 PDF files, 3 MP3 audio files, and 4 WMV video files of electronic publications, approximately 132 megabytes. (Box 5)
  - 2008, 5 folders of print publications. 75 PDF files and 9 WMV video files of electronic publications, approximately 314 megabytes. (Box 5)
  - 2009, 4 folders of print publications. 57 PDF files and 2 WMV video files of electronic publications, approximately 130 megabytes. (Box 5)
  - Manual de Capacitacion en Derechos Humanos y Salud Sexual Reproductiva, 2009; Electronic files derived from an optical disc. Files are executable in modern Windows computer environments. Approximately 350 files, 450 megabytes.
  - 2010, 1 of 5 folders of print publications. 42 PDF files of electronic publications, approximately 42 megabytes. (Box 5)
  - 2010, folders 2 to 5 (Box 6)
  - Film reels, 7 reels (Box 6)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 30-31)
  - Publications with significant contributions from Ipas (Box 32-33)
  - Non-Ipas audio-visual materials (Box 65-66)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 20-22; 67-68)
  - Ipas audio-visual materials (Box 74)
  - Video tapes from "Expanding Access: The Role of Mid-Level Providers in Menstrual Regulation and Elective Abortion Care", Dec 2-5, 2001; miscellaneous video tapes (Box 75-76)
  - undated publications (Box 77)
  - Ipas publications, 1988-2003 (Box 78)
  - Ipas publications, 2004-2011 (Box 79)
  - Ipas publications, binders, and videotapes (Box 80-83)
  - Ipas publications missing from previous shipments: 1992-2011 (Box 109)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 119)
  - 3 oversized Ipas publications (Box 128)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 150-151)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 190)
  - Ipas publications 2012-2013; missing publications from earlier accessions (Box 193)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 195)
  - Ipas publications, 2014-2015 (Box 207)
  - Ipas publications missing from previous shipments (Box 208)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 209)
  - 7 reels of reel-to-reel film: "Population: The alternatives" with Malcolm Potts (2 reels) "Population" – 2 reels Surgical procedures by Len Laufe (2 reels) "Bangladesh: A Physician's training program: - 1 reel "the Missed Period" – 1 reel (Box 229)
  - Ipas website, 2011-2020; 2011-ongoing
  - Ipas YouTube Channel, 2012-2020; 2012-ongoing
  - Ipas Facebook page
  - 2016 publications, non-Ipas publications, 2016 and undated (Box 232)
- Marketing/T&L/PPD, 1973-2009; 10 boxes
  Ipas was founded in 1973 to complete development of the Manual Vacuum Aspirator (MVA) technology and to undertake its distribution worldwide with the overarching goal of ending women's preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion. Ipas focused its MVA marketing and distribution efforts on the product's attributes as a safe, low cost medical instrument appropriate for all types of health care facilities, especially low-resource and outpatient settings where trained mid- and lower-level clinical providers (in addition to physicians) could provide these critical services for women.
  Ipas dedicated staff to its MVA marketing efforts starting in the early 1990s. Starting in 1997, major grants allowed the organization to greatly expand marketing efforts by hiring marketing professionals, undertaking country-based marketing activities to improve local access and supply, positioning MVA as a safe and appropriate alternative to other post-abortion and abortion methodologies, forming private and public partnerships for product distribution, performing more sophisticated market segmentation analyses, expanding the product line, and increasing training options and tools. Sales and distribution of MVA increased dramatically accordingly, resulting in more women being served worldwide. Ipas also re-designed the MVA aspirator to make it more durable, easier to use and maintain, and lower in cost; the new MVA was launched in 2004.
  Ipas's marketing efforts were under the direction of various staff during this time period. Katie Early (McLaurin) headed up marketing activities in the 1980s, and Jennifer Potts was International Marketing Associate in the 1990s. Starting in 1997, Kim Beer was the first Director of Marketing and Gil Barner joined in 2000 as Vice President of Reproductive Health Technologies. The unit was renamed Technology and Logistics (T&L), followed by Product, Promotion and Distribution (PPD) between 2000 and 2004. Darryl Rubenchik became Vice President of PPD in 2002, followed by Nadine Burton in 2003 and Jay Drosin in 2004, and Denise Harrison in 2005. The unit was eliminated in 2009, when separate entity WomanCare Global was formed to take over manufacturing and distribution of MVA instruments.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Series restricted for 10 years after initial transfer to persons who receive prior permission from the President and CEO of Ipas or his/her designee.
  - Annual MVA Sales summaries 75-95; historical marketing 92-95; board presentation 00; customer service 99-01; sales training 97; 1st in-service 97; 2nd in-service 98; 3rd in-service 98; in-service materials 98; marketing orientation 98; marketing team 97; 1st team mtg 97; 2nd team mtg 97; 3rd team mtg 98; updates 98-99; presentations 97-98; presentations 01; price lists prior to 00; price reductions 00; private sector training 00-02; FDA 01; Mozambique MA flipchart notebook; distributor training 97; MVA FAQs 00-03; Vietnam MOH mtg 01; Mombassa Scale-up mtg presentation 00; launch workshop 05; Vietnam RHP presentation 01; troubleshooting guide 00; QA equipment inspections 03; individual distributor files 90-01 (Box 34)
  - Donor proposals and corresp, partner organizations: 1997 – 2001: donor corres 97-00; donor grant 98-00; drawdown 98; drawdown 99; global marketing proposal pilot 96; marketing proposal 97; marketing proposal 98; marketing year one report 98-99; donor corresp 98; marketing donor mtg 99; marketing year two report 99-00; donor mtg 02; marketing year three report 01-02; donor corres 00-01; training and pre-launch donor report 02; expanding access proposal 01-03; partner orgs 00-01; PAC scale-up mtg 00; Concept Foundation 99; FPIA 97-98; IPPF 98; MSI 00-01; MSF 00-01; NGO Networks for Health 00; PAC Consortium 00-01; PAC sustainability 00-01; sustainability paper/presentation 00; PATH 99-00; PAI 00; PDA 02; PRIME 98-00; internships 98-99; UNFPA 00-01; UNICEF 98; UNFPA 99; USAID 01-02; World Bank 97-00 (Box 35)
  - Marketing strategy binder 97-98; Manual/binder for MVA training projects 1994; clinical and programmatic literature on MVA 2003; Marketing R&D files (MVA re-design and launch, Denniston dilators, emergency kit; rigid cannulae tests) (Box 36)
  - Country files (alphabetical) (Box 37-40)
  - J Potts marketing 94-96, management 97-00, E/C Europe marketing plan 00, East Africa marketing plan 00-05, distribution 01-02, UNC School of Public Health project 02, internal newsletters 02-03, internal presentation 05, Europe MAP 05, sales reports 05, MVA Access Plan 05, PPD Educ and promotional materials 05, US program marketing 05, ME/Europe marketing plan 06, pricing study 06-07, distributor survey analysis 06, MAP interim donor report 06, product dossiers 06, donation analysis 06, Albania 05, Denmark 05, Bulgaria 06, Egypt 06, Georgia 05, Iran 06, Kuwait 06, Russia 04, Syria 06, Turkey 06, UAE 06, UK 07 (Box 105)
  - MVA Redesign and Launch 01-05: Redesign chrono 01-02, branding 02, chrono 02-03, chrono 01-03, chrono 04-05, Global Launch mtg 05 (Box 106)
  - Report on 4 Classes on MVA Double-Valve Syringe 97; EasyGrip Trademark Search 02; Reports/Donations Analysis 05; Consultant reports 06; Marketing materials 05; competition 05-07; meetings/planning 06; Taiwan 07; HPSRX 07; Cambodia 07-09; Armenia 08; Canada 08; RH/RA & Abortion seminar – Malaysia 09; Korea 09 (Box 139)
- Latin American and Caribbean Programs, 1987-2010; 30 boxes
  Ipas's first Latin America/Caribbean (LAC) programs began in Mexico in 1983 with demonstration training projects in MVA technique for treating abortion complications. Extensive programs, primarily in training for women's reproductive health service delivery and health systems research, were conducted starting in the late 1980s. The primary LAC program countries from 1987 - 2003 were Mexico, Nicaragua, Brazil and Bolivia (all of which had in-country Ipas offices over this time period), with smaller projects at various times in Peru, Paraguay, Colombia and Chile. Ipas has sold MVA instruments throughout the entire continent. By the mid-1990s, Ipas stepped up efforts in policy and marketing in the LAC region, as overall organizational capacity was enhanced in these areas.
  Areas of highest impact and results in the LAC region by Ipas include: assisting governments in national scale-up of post abortion care initiatives to improve quality of and access to treatment of abortion complications, contributing to reductions in maternal mortality; research cost studies on services; quality of care and instructional tools for improving post abortion care services and preventing repeat abortion via post abortion family planning; establishing legal abortion services where laws have allowed; provision of post abortion care services by mid-level and primary care providers; reproductive health services for adolescents; publicizing the issue of sexual violence against women; and advancement of women's sexual and reproductive rights as part of human rights.
  Ipas's LAC programs were under the direction of various staff during this time period - most notably Ann Leonard (Program Officer in the late 1980s), followed by Harrison McKay (Director of Programs), Joan Healy (Director of Programs in the 1990s), Virginia Chambers, Ipas's first LAC Desk Director (regional director) from 1998-2008, and Christopher Bross (regional manager, then regional director) starting in 2008.
  - Mexico: donor proposals and reports; Frente/Campana project; IMSS sol files; ILE files; Monterey Symposium files; country annual report; adolescents; nursing schools; monthly reports; pro-choice alliance files; small grants program; video proposal; country workplan; SE project; Alianza; sexual violence, 2001-2003 (Box 7)
  - Mexico: photos of trainings; Access project files; mid-level project files; ILE project files; IMSS Sol; Mexico office trip reports; monthly reports; Mexico country plan; Mexico program summaries; job descriptions and benefits; training numbers, 2000 (Box 8)
  - Mexico: Legal Abortion project files; IMSS files; mid-level rural project files; Mexico office communications; trip reports; AAA-World Bank project files; Access (marketing) project files, 1999 (Box 9-10)
  - Mexico: marketing files; IMSS-Sol project files; modules project files; SSA project files; Morelos project files; Safe Motherhood; Mexico office communications; training numbers, trip reports; radio spots; Dr. Ortiz, 1998 (Box 11)
  - Mexico: correspondence; 2nd USAID PAC meeting files; IMSS Solidaridad project files; marketing files; Morelos files; sustaining file; INOPAL files; 1997 (Box 12)
  - Mexico: IMSS project files; SSA project files; Merelos project files; USAID PAC meeting project files; Mexico office communications; Mexico sustaining program file; APHA abstract; PAC strategy meeting, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Mexico: training notebook; Mihoacan/Zacatecas; Sinora/Sinaloa program files; INPER; Geo Gonzales; Safe Motherhood; IMSS; Pathfinder project; Oaxaca; proposals/reports; legal docs; MVA licensing, 1987-1995 (Box 14)
  - PERU 88-97: comms with practitioners 88-91; background 90-92; field proposals 91-92; trip reports 90-92; letters 91; donor proposals 92; corresp 92; corresp 93; corresp 94; Movimento Manuela Ramos project files 94-95: evaluation, comms Pathfinder, comms Manuelas, comms others; Pathfinder training 95: contracts/planning, reports, comms; INOPAL project files 95-97: planning, MINSA, background, proposals/workplan/report, comms Pop Council and USAID, comms others, qualitative study, results/eval, trip reports; legal documents 96-01; data collection forms 96-97; INOPAL mtg Honduras 97; INOPAL assessments 97; general 97; SPOG project files 97: reports/proposal, background, comms, 1988-1997 (Box 15)
  - Brazil, Peru, Paraguay, Columbia, Chile: working files; Facultad de Obstetricia project files; midwifery schools; proposals; ICM presentations; PAC/PAFP meeting; marketing; reports, correspondence; fundraising; MVA in medical schools; proposals; country plan; workplan; Ayacucho project; project development; Flora Tristan; dissemination workshop; collaboration; correspondence; management cycle; working files; Araucania project files, 1993-2002 (Box 16)
  - LAC miscellaneous countries without programs 89-00: Argentina 89-00 – background, orgs, corresp; Chile 89-98 – background, corresp; Colombia 92-95 – background, project development; Cuba 91-99 – background, trip reports, corresp; Dominican Republic 87-95 – background, corresp; Ecuador trip reports 88; El Salvador 92-95 – background, orgs, corresp, trip reports; Guatemala 90-98 – background, corresp, Dr. Kestler, Safe Motherhood conf; Guyana 98-02 – background, corresp; Haiti 99-02 – background, NGOs; Honduras 89-97 – background, corresp, trip reports; Uruguay project development 93; Venezuela 99 (Box 17)
  - LAC regional management and planning working files 94-03: project development background 94; donor proposals and reports 95; PAC training workshop Mexico 96; PAC strategies 98; DFID regional initiatives 98; results 98; novedades 99; desk objectives 99; regional objectives 99; planning models 99; team development 99; marketing 99; regional reports 99; projects 99; regional planning mtg 99 – logistics, overheads, results; materials/handouts, proceedings; LAC strategic management team 99-00; desk objectives 00; divisional objectives 00; regional summary 00; regional update for Ipas management 00; staff mtg 00; regional update presentation 00; staff orientation 01; regional planning 01; annual objectives 01; country office systems 01; pubs 01; structure task force 01; team mtgs 01; regional planning 02; regional planning 03; LAC partner organizations 89-99: Orientame 91-99; ALIRH 95-97, PAC Consortium 96; PRIME 99; Frontiers; Pathfinder 93-95; PPFA LAC 91-92; Catholicas por el derecho a decider 92-93; CEDPA 91; CLAP 93; FCI 90-93; FHI 89-94; IWHC 89-94; JPIEGO 89; MSI 92; IPPF; PAHO 92-99; PATH 90-92; Pop Concern 97; Euro Commission 97-98; ODA; UNFPA; World Bank (Box 18)
  - LAC Regional Projects: LART 96 – donor corresp, agenda, conf materials, planning, corresp Ortiz, corresp Elsa, corresp Andrea, participants, general, Miscellaneous, participant responses, photos; AVSC MTG Mexico 95-96 – mtg program 96, other, proposal/contract, report, workplan, overheads, reports, planning, other corresp; FLASOG Paraguay 96 – proposal/reports, contracts, corresp; PRIME LAC-PAC 97 – proposal/workplan, comms Blandon/Ortiz, comms FECASOG, comms AID, comms others, contacts; comms participants, reports; LAC-PAC TWG 97 – FECASOG proposal/budget, contract/corresp, comms, emails/corresp, parts list/program, sister org, ideas, Bolivia parts, Honduras parts, Mexico parts, Paraguay parts, Peru parts; FLASOG 00; FECASOG 00; FLASOG 02; UNFPA 02-03 (Box 19)
  - BOLIVIA 93/94/95: Bolivia II 92-93 – background, donor, field proposals, contracts/contacts, trip reports, field reports, eval, comms ICR, comms general; Bolivia 94 – proposals/workplan, donor, trip reports, background, contracts/contacts, field proposal, Pop Council, eval/research, comms Susanna Rance, comms general, reports; Bolivia 95 – ODA, background, donor, USAID reports, contracts, corresp ICR, corresp MOH, corresp general, trip reports, field reports, press articles (Box 23)
  - BOLIVIA 96/97/98: Bolivia 96 – background, contacts/contracts, comms general, comms Susanna, comms ICR, comms MOH, press articles, financials, trip reports, Pop Council mtg, eval/complications; ODA Bolivia 97 – background, proposal/budget, reports, comms, comms S Rance, comms MOH; Bolivia 97 – comms in-country rep, ODA files – field reports, other reports, trip reports, contracts, comms other; INOPAL 97; Bolivia DFID INOPAL Year Two 98 – background/articles, proposal/budget, comms DFID, eval/complications, trip reports, legal documents, contracts/CVs, comms del Pozo, reports Rance, comms Rance, comms other, comms USAID, comms MOH, grant agreement and extension, financials, trip reports (Box 24)
  - Bolivia: DFID working files; DFID final report; training numbers; country plan; correspondence; proposals; trip reports; logframe; reach numbers, 1999-2000 (Box 25)
  - Bolivia: team meetings; correspondence; monthly reports; evaluations; marketing; DFID working files; Frontiers working files; reach numbers; violence symposium; program review; fundraising; USAID PAC evaluation; development consultant; medical/nursing schools; site coordinators; reach numbers; management cycle, 2001-2003 (Box 26)
  - Bolivia 89-98 Background 89-90; renewal of MOU 94-99; ODA 95-96; Susanna Rance 97; Cochabamba data 97; PAC assessment 97-98; DFID reports 97-00; national program for adolescents 98; M&E presentation 98; LA strategic plan 98; UNFPA 98; attitudes/opinions study 98; Pop Council report 98; DFID country strategy paper 98; DFID mtgs 98; abortion background 98; project indicators USAID 98; UNFPA 98; S Rance workplan 98; DFID Year 2 + INOPAL FY 98 working files: background/news articles, contracts/CVs, communications USAID, communications Pop Council; comms MOH, comms DFID, comms S Rance, comms other, comms INOPAL researcher, reports from Eliana del Pozo, reports from S. Rance. (Box 147)